<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the camp of Israel (whom He hath brought up out of the land of Egypt by a mighty hand and outstretched arm) called Quakers in England (or elsewhere upon the face of the earth) a visitation and dear salutation from the breathings of the life of a true Jew ... / by William Bayly.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18148</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12395509</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12395509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61149</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27138)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61149)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 270:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the camp of Israel (whom He hath brought up out of the land of Egypt by a mighty hand and outstretched arm) called Quakers in England (or elsewhere upon the face of the earth) a visitation and dear salutation from the breathings of the life of a true Jew ... / by William Bayly.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61149:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61149:1"/>
            <head>To the Camp of Iſrael, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY dearly beloved Friends, Brethren and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who are of the ſtook of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and Seed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who are brought, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of the Land of darkneſs, and houſe of bondage, by the out-ſtretched Arm of the Almighty <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to follow him who is an everlaſting Light, into the Heavenly Land of reſt and peace, which endureth for ever; who are of <hi>Caleb</hi> &amp; <hi>Joſhua's</hi> ſpirit, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſigned to do or ſuffer the Wil of God in all things in your generation, who are the true Iſraelites indeed, without guile, partiality or hypocriſie, the <hi>choſen generation,</hi> the Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, zealous for God &amp; good works, &amp; valiant for the Truth upon earth, who can forſake all to follow the Lamb in his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of patience, long-ſuffering, love and meekneſs, wiſdom and fear, bearing all things, enduring all things, hoping al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in God, and rejoicing in tribulations, glorying in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſaving in the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, reſolving in his ſtrength with purpoſe of heart to cleave faſt unto the Lord, though your outward man periſh or be offered up as a living ſacrifice for his holy Name and Truth: I ſay, that you truly are my brethren and ſiſters; I have no greater joy than to ſit down with you, and feed with you at your Table, which indeed is no leſs then the Table of the Lord which he hath ſpread for us; yea, even when we were in the Wilderneſs did he give us Manna from Heaven, Angels food, and water out of the Rock which then followed us; bleſſed for ever be the Lord and the remembrance of his Name. And when I call to mind theſe things, and the multitude of his mercies and endleſſe compaſſions which he ſhewed towards us in the days of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, when he took us by the hand, and taught us to go; my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61149:2"/> bowels are turned within me, and I am melted before the Lord. O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what hath thy God done for thee! Stand ſtil a little, and conſider how he hath dealt with thee in the days paſt; whether he hath dealt ſo with any Nation; how he hath made Rivers in the Deſart, and the dry Land to become ſprings of Water: How hath he filled the hungry with good things, and ſent the rich empty away! He hath brought down the mighty from their ſeats, and exalted them of low degree: He hath made the Wilderneſs a fruitful field, and turned the fruitful Land into barrenneſſe, becauſe of the iniquity of them that dwelt therein. He hath divided the ſea, and made it ſtand on heaps while his choſen Remnant paſſeth over, He hath overthrown the horſe and his Rider; he hath pierced Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan, and bruiſed the head of the crooked Serpent, and broken the great teeth and jaws of the wicked; he hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the mouth of the Lyon, and from the paw of the Bear, and from the uncircumciſed Philiſtins: He hath made the Lame to leap as an Hart and the Tongue of the dumb to ſing. He hath ſet the ſolitary in Families, and is leading <hi>Joſeph</hi> like a Flock, and making him Ruler over <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Land of darkneſs. O magnifie the Name of the Lord all ye children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and let the inhabitants of the Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k ſing for joy, for great and marvellous things hath the Lord done for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; he hath raiſed the dead, and brought <hi>Lazarni</hi> from the grave: He hath opened the eyes of the born blind; he hath cleanſed the Lepers, and caſt out Devils, and they are gone into the Herd of Swine. He hath fed a great multitude with a little portion, and yet much remains. He hath cured the daughter of <hi>Abraham</hi> which was bowed down many years. He hath ſtopt the running iſſue, which all the Phyſicians of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue could never do. He hath made a Hedge about <hi>Job,</hi> and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered juſt <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and brought him to <hi>Zoar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things hath the Lord of Life done among us, of which we are eye-witneſſes; and his own Arm, hath brought ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hath wrought all our Works in us, and for us, which none other man could do. O praiſe the Lord for ever, all ye that have breath in the Land of the living, and let the ſons of <hi>Jacob</hi> have him and his works in everlaſting remembrance. If we forget his mercies ſhewed unto <hi>Zion,</hi> and his wonders in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61149:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> deep, let our right hand forget her cunning: If I forget thee, O <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and what thy God hath done for thee, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth: But how is my ſoul become as a watered Garden, in brokenneſs and humility be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord God of our ſalvation, when I call to mind his tender mercies and dealings of old; and when <hi>I</hi> remember the Wormwood and the Gall, and how there was none found worthy in Heaven nor Earth to open the Book, and to looſe the ſeals, neither to look thereon, but the Lamb which had been ſlain; then was the time of weeping and of great mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as in the Valley of <hi>Haddadrimmon;</hi> yea even apart in the Wilderneſs and ſolitary places. O Lord God, ſhall thy people ever forget theſe things, and thy wonders upon the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which thou wroughteſt for thy Seeds ſake, and the great ſalvation which thou haſt ſhewed to <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Shall there ever be an image made, or the likeneſs of any thing in Heaven or in Earth, to be bowed down to, but thy Name alone, which is and ſhall be exalted above every Name, in which thy babes and children have found comfort, ſtrength and ſafety to this day? Or ſhall any thing ſit in thy Judgement-ſeat with thee, but that which overcometh, and is thy Son? is not all power in Heaven and Earth, and all Judgement committed to him in whoſe mouth is found no guile, who is meek and lowly in heart, who looſed the ſeals, and opened the Book, and did prevail, and hath prevailed over the Dragon and his Angels; who makes war in righteouſneſs, and in it goes on conquering and to conquer: who hath the Keys of Death and of Hell. Therefore let your eyes be alone unto him, O ye followers of the Lamb, and fear not man, neither look unto man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils; but be valiant for the Truth upon Earth, which endureth for ever. Follow your Captain, even of your ſalvation, ye White-Horſe-men, who are of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that are in Heaven, whoſe clothing is white and clean, and your Armor the whole Armor of Light, having on the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of a meek, quiet and patient ſpirit, which is of great price in the ſight of God, though in it you appear as fools in the ſight of men: You are of that Troop which ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come at the laſt, though you ſeem as to the outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61149:3"/> to be overcome and trampled under foot for a ſeaſon, for the exerciſe and trial of your faith and patience, through which God is bringing his Lambs nearer to his boſom, though their face is marred more then any mans, and their form more then the ſons of men. But the Lord of Hoſts is with you, and the ſhout of a King is among you, which ſhall make Nations to tremble, and the beaſts of the field to flye before him. The Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> hath roared out of <hi>Zion,</hi> and hath uttered his voice from his holy Temple <hi>New-Jeruſalem,</hi> and he it is that muſt get the victory, and have the dominion and reign, til all his Enemies are become his footſtool. This is the Lords doing, and this Work he wil accompliſh by his own arm; therefore lift up your heads ye babes and ſuckling children of the moſt High, and be bold in the ſtrength of the Almighty, and in it be very couragious in this the day of his power: Feel <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua's</hi> ſpirit ſtirred up, which ſaith, <hi>We will go on, the Lord will go before us, and he will fight our battels, and we ſhall prevail:</hi> For the Battel is the Lords, the Work is the Lords, and he wil accompliſh it; the day is his, the ſet-time is come, and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory is and muſt be his: Here you dwel in the pure ſence and feeling of the noble Plant of renown, the right Seed, which wil wholly follow the Lord; this his ſoul takes pleaſure in, and he wil never forſake it, though a Woman may forſake her child; this will never draw back becauſe of perſecutions, threatnings or fiery tryals, Fornace or Den of Lyons; but puts on the whole Armour of God; and is clad with zeal as with a Cloak, and ſets its face like a Flint, becauſe of truth, and becauſe of righteouſneſſe. This is the Royal birth which God hath raiſed and wil raiſe, to whom the Kingdom and Dominion belongs forevermore; it's againſt this the enmity is; the Devil and the Dragons malice is againſt this Child, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter its Blood the Whore, Beaſt, Dragon and falſe Prophet have thirſted from <hi>Cain</hi> unto this day: This is the Lamb that hath been ſlain from the foundation of the World. This is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Child againſt whom <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and all the <hi>Rulers</hi> took counſel in all ages againſt the holy Child; not ſo much againſt Profeſſion is their aim, but at the Life and holy Birth it ſelf, which is born and manifeſt in fleſh, which hath been the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61149:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> hidden from ages and generations, but now is, and ſhall be manifeſt more and more through all theſe tryals and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, to the ends of the earth. This is he whoſe Veſture is dipt in blood, whom the Armies in Heaven follow; in heaven, not in earth, or of the earth are his Armies; but in heaven, making War in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe, patience &amp; long-ſuffering: This is his heavenly Army that ſhal overcome with him, and get the victory over the Beaſt, the Dragon, the Whore and the falſe Prophet; the Lord God that lives for ever hath ſpoken it: The Lamb muſt overcom, and the Kingdom, and the greatneſs of it ſhall be given to the Saints of the moſt high, and they ſhall poſſeſs it even to the end.</p>
            <p>Therefore fear not ye little Flock, whoſe breathing hearts are upright before God, Angels and men, who have the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in you, that you ſeek nothing but Truth, Righteouſneſſe and Peace with God and Man, and have no end but the glory of God and the exaltation of his Name, by the raiſing of his Seed, and the ſalvation of the ſouls of the children of men, whoſe feeding is in the green paſtures, which lie in the low Valleys by the ſtil Waters of <hi>Shiloh</hi> which run ſoftly. The Lord is with you, though you are as Worms in your own eyes, and are ready to ſay with <hi>Mary, How can this be, ſeeing I know not a man!</hi> I have no might, power, wiſdom, ſtrength or ability of my own. Be but the Virgin, wholly reſigned into the Wil of God, with thine eye ſingle, fixt in thy head, &amp; the power of the Moſt High ſhall overſhadow thee: And the Kingdom of God conſiſteth in power righteouſneſſe and joy in the holy Ghoſt, into which the wiſe Virgins enter, who are the followers of the Lamb (in whoſe mouth is found no guile) through the great tribulations; theſe are the true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, not only in word, but in deed and in truth. Theſe follow him in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and have the white Robes and the Palms given unto them. Theſe ſing the new ſong which no man could learn but they that are redeemed from the Earth. Theſe ſit in the heavenly places with Chriſt Jeſus, upon tvvelve Thrones judging the tvvelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Theſe are they that are beheaded and ſuffer for the Word of God, and the Teſtimony vvhich they hold: Mark, they <hi>hold</hi> it, and do not let it go, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61149:4"/> let go the Earth with the glory, treaſures, delights and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of it; but holds the Teſtimony of Jeſus, and have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the good part with <hi>Mary,</hi> which endures for ever, and lets go the cumbrings with the many things, for the one only needful thing, the Word of God, which is the Word of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, of Life, of Patience, of Reconciliation, and of Wiſdom, which ſaves the immortal ſoul, which is but one Word which was in the beginning, with whom <hi>Enoch</hi> walked, and was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, which is God the Judge of all, unto which we are come, and to the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the City of the living God, and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, where is no occaſion of ſtumbling, but God is the Judge of all, who brings the hidden things to light; but before this is witneſſed, there may be ſtumbling and occaſions of ſtumbling, and a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be given (before the Lord come) in the unjuſt mans ſpirit, which is for Judgement. But take heed of this thing, I charge, and alſo beſeech thee, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the Word of the Lord that liveth and abideth for ever, as thou loveſt his holy Name, the peace and proſperity of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the welfare of thine own ſoul: But live in the Word of Wiſdom and true Authority and patience of the Lamb, and dwell with God the Judge of all, in whoſe righteous Judgement, and before whoſe Throne judge thy ſelf, and let the beam be plucked out of every eye that would preſume to judge before the time; and let the dread of the Lord be before it; for it is a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing to uſurp Authority over Chriſt Jeſus, which is the man that muſt judge the World in righteouſneſs, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with Truth, who ſaith to his Diſciples, <hi>Be ye merciful as your heavenly Father is merciful:</hi> And they who are children of their Heavenly Father, are not apt to judge raſhly before the time, out of his counſel, truth, power, wiſdom and fear; but rather wait in patience until the Time comes (even the Lord) who bringeth the hidden things to light, having an eye to the glory of God, and the good part in all people, as well as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the people: Theſe have no reſpect of perſons, neither admire mens perſons for advantage ſake. Theſe are not in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice or evil ſurmizings againſt any, knowing God's hand is going over all theſe things, who is the Judg of all; for where any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61149:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> prejudice, reſpect of perſons, with the beam in the eye, lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the heart of any man, in that ſtate that man's Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is unjuſt and unrighteous, who ever he be; (J ſpeak from God without partiality:) He hath not the mercy that God hath to the unjuſt; and the very Sun in the Firmament will teach that man wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Therefore my dearly beloved Friends, Brethren and Siſters, with whom I am bound up in the bundle of Life, to live and to dye in, and for the righteous Cauſe and Work of God, which is his Truth that endureth for ever; this is my exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto you all from the leaſt to the greateſt, without reſpect of perſons or things outward: In the bowels of unfeigned love look all at the good part which is of God in your ſelves, and dwel in the good part, in the remembrance of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and loving-kindneſs which he hath ſhewed unto you; and ſhut your eyes from ſeeing of evil, and look only at the good part in all; then wil you anſwer the good part in <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,</hi> and the Church of God. Here you ſhall be able to dwel with everlaſting burnings, and in the Munition of Rocks. Here ye dwell with God the Judge of all, and the ſpirits of juſt men. Here's every high imagination and every thought that would exalt ſelf, brought down through the Judgement of God, into the obedience of Chriſt. Here's that unjuſt ſpirit judged which would take the neighbour or brother by the throat, or lay hands ſuddenly on any, which <hi>Paul</hi> charged <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> not to do.</p>
            <p>Therefore all ye dear children of God, keep out of that ſpirit, and let it not have place in you, no not for a moment; but dwell in the life and wiſdom of God the Judge of all, where you wil feel the juſt man's ſpirit, which can judge and try all things, and be eſtabliſhed in it; for I have conſidered that this is a day of great trials and temptations on every hand, and of the making manifeſt them that are approved in God's ſight. It is a day which requires retiredneſſe, fear, watchfulneſſe and diligence, which wil keep out of being ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily moved or provoked: But your hearts will come to be eſtabliſhed in power, love, and a found mind, in which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61149:5"/> your compaſſions will flow forth towards your brethren, and towards all men; and ye will feel mercy ariſe, and pitty towards Enemies: Dwelling your ſelves alwayes in the ſenſe and feeling of God's Mercies, Compaſſions and Long-ſuffering towards you. I ſpeak what I know through the exerciſe of my faith and patience concerning theſe things; and I have found, That the thought of preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and evil ſurmizing againſt any man or creature whatſoever, is judged with the Life of the true Seed (which lives in the boſome of God, the Judge of all, which can ſtand upon the Sea of Glaſs mingled with Fire) to be of the Enmity which came of the old crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Serpent, the beguiler and ſeparater from the Tree of Life; Here you'l ſee the Tale-bearers, which ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth very Friends, of which Wiſdom ſpake to be very near.</p>
            <p>The Lord open your underſtandings (my dear friends) for my bowels and very heart is open towards you, with deſires and prayers to God for all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> That they might be ſaved from the Wrath which is to come as a Flood upon the ungodly and rebellious generation.</p>
            <p>And the Lord God of Mercies and Bleſſings keep us all in meekneſſe and fear, in his Spirit of Lowlineſſe, Love and Forbearance, in tenderneſſe, forgiving and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another, as God for Chriſt (his Seed's) ſake hath forgiven us; ſhutting that eye that looks af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Moat, for that is the evil eye, the Hypocrite gone out from, and exalted above the Heir, the Life of God, to which the Judgement and the Power is committed: This ſhall never inherit true peace with God or Man in that ſtate: For evil thoughts lodging, and being joined unto, defile a man, and ſhuts that Kingdom againſt him, into which no unclean thing can enter.</p>
            <p>So my dear Friends, and all you whoſe faces are turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed toward the Paradice of God, from the Earth, into which ye were driven by tranſgreſſion: Mind theſe things, and let this remembrance be alwayes freſh in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61149:5"/> you, that you bear not the Root, but the Root bear you: And this will keep you, that you ſhall not be high-minded, but fear; and to be little in your own eyes, as the little Child, unto whom the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God belongs.</p>
            <p>And this Spirit (before-mentioned) of forgiveneſs, mercies and long-ſuffering, love unfeigned, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and patience, dwelling in the watchfulneſſe for good (in the Wiſdom of God) and not for evil, is the Spirit of the Lamb, whom the Lord hath ſaid, (and fully determined) That it ſhall proſper and ſpread through Nations, and it ſhall have dominion over them, and they ſhall bow to it, and it ſhall be a bleſſing unto many people and Nations afar off; and the everlaſting preſence and bleſſings of the Almighty ſhall accompany it for ever; and the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it: But that which is raſh, high, heady, proud, wilful, fooliſh and ſtubborn (in which the Leven of the Phariſees lodgeth) God will lay low, and abaſe before him; and all Judgement which is not his Sons (in whom he is well-pleaſed, to whom all Judgement is committed and belongs) he will judge and condemn: And he that judgeth before he is to me, who is Lord and Judge of all (and without him) God will judge.</p>
            <p>So in the Spirit of the Lamb, dear Babes and Children of Light, go on and proſper, and be faithful and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant for the Truth upon the Earth, keeping low in your own meaſure, every one marching in his own path; then your Ranks will not be broken; for thus is it written of the Camp of the Lord which muſt get the victory; for the Enemy is very buſie, ſtriving every way to draw forth your ſimple minds from the ſtrong hold of the Priſon of Hope. Therefore bleſſed is he that watcheth and waiteth alway at Wiſdoms gate, for there is the ſimple preſerved in meekneſs and fear, love and patience, godlineſs and brotherly kindneſs, which is the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61149:6"/> moſt excellent way. This is the path where the Lyon cannot come, nor any ravenous Beaſt can touch this Mountain, but hee'l be ſtruck through with the ſling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of <hi>David,</hi> or a Dart of God's righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Here's no deſtroying nor hurting in all this holy Mountain, but bearing all things, enduring all things without murmuring, complaining or envying, dwelling in that love which thinks no evil: This is that Spirit of the Lamb of God which ſaveth ſouls, and overcometh or taketh away a Multitude of ſins, wherein is no delight to lay open the Brother's naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (for that's of <hi>Ham</hi>'s ſtock, which God hath cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever) but rather a ſecret crying to the Lord concerning ſuch things, (O that thy Name might not ſuffer nor be reproached through any who profeſs thy everlaſting Name and Truth) and can ſay as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did, <hi>Blot out my Name, rather then thy Name ſhould ſuffer, or be juſtly reproached or diſhonored amongſt thy people.</hi> This is that which is raiſed in many, which they love more then Father, Mother, Wife, Children, Houſe or Lands, yea, or their own Life, as God is witneſſe. Here's a paſſage through the daily Croſs, the ſtrait gate into the place of broad Rivers, where goes no galley with Oars, but a ſtretching forth and ſwimming in the Eternal Will and Obedience of God.</p>
            <p>So lift up your Heads, all ye tender Plants of my Heavenly Fathers own planting, from the virtue which you receive at the Root of <hi>David,</hi> from which the branch of Righteouſneſs ſprings; and dwell in the ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and patience, in which ye will feel the bowels of God's Love and Mercies opened in you like a Fountain, at which ye may drink and be ſatisfied, and rejoice in God your Saviour, in the midſt of all Tryals and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, wherein ye wil have ſtrength and boldneſs to confeſs his Name before men, even to the death, in the day when many ſhall hide themſelves for fear, and for looking at the things which are ſwiftly coming
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61149:6"/> upon the Earth. So dear Babes of God, and Children of the Stock of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> put on the whole Armour of Light, and make War in Righteouſneſs, in the Spirit of the Lamb, in whoſe mouth guile is not found; this is the Captain of our Salvation, who hath left us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, vvhom looking to, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying, the Lord God that made Heaven and Earth wil be with you, and preſerve you all his dear children in and through all your tryals and tribulations, which may be ſuffered to come upon you for the tryal of your faith and patience; and for the purifying and cleanſing his ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary: And this Man wil be your hiding place from the ſtorm and from the rain, even the ſame which was found, the Rock, in a weary Land: And this is he that vvil ſtand the laſt upon the Earth, and get the Victory and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over and through all, of whoſe Dominion and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhal be no end.</p>
            <p>So in this the Lord God of Life, of Heaven and Earth, keep you all by his Eternal power, and eſtabliſh you on the unmovable Rock of ſalvation, that ſo with one heart, mind and ſoul, we may glorifie the holy Name of our God in this our Day and Generation, and right walking before him, that ſo we may give up our account with joy, and not with grief, and have the Witneſs in us and for us, that we are vvel-pleaſing in his ſight; in which whether vve live or dye, vve ſhal have peace, and joy unſpeakable and ful of glory.</p>
            <p>The Lord God of Life, Love and Peace; Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs, be vvith you all my dear Brethren and Friends, and preſerve you all in his Eternal povver unto his Heavenly Kingdom, there to remain, and in it to reſt, when this World ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is given forth in the movings of the Bowels of God's Love, unto his people Iſrael, and in the remembrance of his mercies of old, and of his daily compaſſions towards them, which is as an entreaty thereby, that we may all remember and lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e his mercies, walking
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61149:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> humbly before him all the dayes of your life. And to be read in your Meetings as in wiſdom and conveniency of time ye have meet opportunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Companion of them that follow the Lamb through the great tribulations, for whoſe ſake he can ſay he loves not his life to the death, enjoying that Love which is ſtronger then death: Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord forever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61149:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
